Chocolate has been long
maligned when it comes to acne.
But is it the cocoa itself
or the sugar and dairy
that come with it
that causes acne?
Watch to find out.
"Do Chocolate and Cocoa
Powder Cause Acne?"
Acne affects nearly 1 in
10 people in the world,
making it perhaps the eighth
most prevalent disease worldwide.
What’s the role of nutrition?
Well, go back a century
and dermatology textbooks
were recommending various
dietary restrictions.
For example, recommending
those with acne
avoid foods like pork, sausage, cheese,
pickles, pastries, sweets,
cocoa, and chocolate.
Yeah, but old-timey medicine
was full of crackpot theories.
Dr. Kellogg, for example,
blamed acne on masturbation.
Nothing a few corn flakes
couldn’t fix though...
Population studies have
found associations
between acne and the
consumption of foods
like dairy, sweets, and chocolate,
but you don’t know if
it’s cause and effect...
until you put it to the test.
There have been high quality reports,
like the Harvard Nurse’s study,
that looked at nearly 50,000 women
and found a link between adolescent
milk drinking and acne,
particularly skim milk,
something that’s been found
for teenage boys as well.
They thought it might be the hormones
in milk that were responsible,
but it could also be
the milk protein, whey,
of which they add
extra to skim milk
to make it less watery,
which may play a role directly
in acne formation or
as hormonal carriers.
That would explain
cases like this:
where whey protein
powders were implicated
in precipitating acne
flares in teens
who had acne that just didn’t
seem to want to go away
until they stopped the whey.
It doesn’t appear to just
be a protein effect,
since soy protein
supplements, for example,
did not seem to cause
the same problem.
But, for dairy, in terms
of interventional studies,
all we have are these
kinds of case series.
If you do a systematic review
of acne and nutrition,
you get results like this for dairy:
out of the 20 or so papers
on acne and dairy out there,
about three-quarters
suggest adverse effects,
and the remainder
report no effect,
with no studies suggesting
a beneficial effect
of dairy on acne;
so, you could look at
this and conclude
a dairy-free diet is worth a try.
But, this is based
on low-grade evidence,
level C and D evidence,
where C is like the
population studies,
and D is kind of like those
series of case reports.
What we want ideally
are randomized
interventional studies,
level A and B evidence,
which we don’t have for dairy,
but we do have for chocolate.
When it comes to acne,
no food is more universally
condemned than chocolate.
So, if you’re the Chocolate
Manufacturers Association,
how are you going
to design a study
to make your product
not look so bad?
Well, you can always use
the old drug company trick
of pitting your product against
something even worse;
and so, they fed people
chocolate bars versus
fake chocolate bars
made out of a partially
hydrogenated vegetable oil:
trans fats.
So, make it have more sugar,
throw in some milk protein,
and make it 28% pure trans fat laden,
Crisco-like vegetable shortening.
And surprise, surprise
there were just as many pimples
on the fake chocolate bars,
allowing them to conclude
that eating high amounts
of chocolate is A-OK
when it comes to acne.
And, the medical community fell for it.
“Have we been guilty of
taking candy away from babies?”
“Too many patients harbor the delusion
that their health can somehow
be mysteriously harmed
by something in their diet.”
That original study “finding
that chocolate consumption
supposedly does not
exacerbate acne
has continued to remain
virtually unchallenged
for decades and continues to be cited”
even in recent reviews.
For example, this pediatrics journal.
Years ago, it was demonstrated
that chocolate consumption
had no effect on acne.
“This serves as a
cautionary example
of how ‘research-
based evidence’
should be vigorously scrutinized
prior to being incorporated
into clinical practice.”
Just because something
is published in the
Journal of the American
Medical Association
doesn’t necessarily mean
it’s a good study,
especially when industry
interests are involved.
Maybe we should be
telling acne patients
to try cutting down on not
only the sweets and the dairy
but also the trans fats
found in partially hydrogenated
vegetable oils,
but we can’t be unequivocal
in our advice to acne sufferers
on foods to include
or exclude until...
they’re put to the test
in well-designed randomized
controlled clinical trials.
But there simply weren’t any
such trials on acne, until...
Now, which we’ll cover, next.
A century ago, diet was commonly used
as part of the treatment for acne.
During the 1960s, however,
the diet–acne connection
fell out of favor.
Why?
Because of a study
purported to “prove”
that chocolate had no
influence on acne
by comparing a chocolate bar
to a pseudo-chocolate bar
composed of 28% pure trans fat
laden partially hydrogenated
vegetable oil,
a substance known to
increase signs of inflammation.
Compared to that, no wonder
that chocolate didn’t come
out looking so bad.
And then, there was
this other study
where small groups of
medical students
ate a variety of
purported culprits
and only about a
third broke out,
but there was no control
group to compare to,
yet these two studies, despite
their “major design flaws,
were sufficient to
dissociate diet from acne
in the minds of
most dermatologists.
Textbooks were revised
to reflect
this new academic consensus,
and dermatologists
took the stance
that any mumblings about
the association
between diet and acne
were unscientific
and one of the many myths
surrounding this ubiquitous disease.”
Comments such as,
“The association of diet
with acne has been relegated
to the category of myth”
are commonplace in
both the past
and current medical literature,
yet the major dermatology
textbooks promulgating this notion
that diet and acne
are unrelated,
rely only on those
two flawed studies.
So, this current thought
within the dermatology community
that diet and acne
are unrelated
has little or no
factual support.
And, there’s reason to suspect
chocolate consumption
may be an issue.
If you take blood from people
before and after eating
a couple of bars
of milk chocolate,
it appears to prime
some of your pus cells
to release extra
inflammatory chemicals,
when you expose them
to acne-causing
bacteria in a petri dish.
So, maybe this is
one of the mechanisms
that could explain the effects
of chocolate on acne,
but how do we know
it’s the chocolate
and not the added
sugar or milk?
Yes, if you survey teens
on their acne severity
and eating habits,
there appears to be a link
to chocolate consumption,
but is that people sprinkling
cocoa powder in their smoothies,
or eating dark chocolate or,
is it because of the
added sugar and milk?
Just cutting down
on sugary foods
and refined grains
can cut pimple counts
in half in a few months,
significantly better
than the control group,
complete with compelling
before and after pictures.
To tease out if
it was the sugar,
researchers gave
people milk chocolate
versus jelly beans.
If it was just the sugar,
then acne would presumably
get equally worse in both groups,
but instead, the chocolate group
got worse—a doubling
of acne lesions,
whereas no change in
the jelly bean group.
So, it’s apparently
not just the sugar,
maybe there is something
in chocolate,
or is it only in
milk chocolate?
So far, there have
been no studies
assessing the effects of pure
100% chocolate on acne,
that is, until...
there were!
57 volunteers with
mild-to-moderate acne
were randomized into three groups,
receiving white
chocolate bars,
dark chocolate bars,
or no chocolate bars
every day for a month.
And, this wasn’t
just dark chocolate,
but 100% chocolate,
meaning like
baker’s chocolate.
Unlike pure dark chocolate,
white chocolate is packed
with sugar and milk.
And, indeed,
acne lesions worsened
in the white
chocolate group,
but not in the dark
chocolate or control groups.
So, in this study,
white, but not dark,
chocolate consumption
was associated
with an exacerbation
of acne lesions.
But, other studies did show acne
worsening on dark chocolate.
Give research subjects
a single big load
of Ghirardelli baking chocolate,
and they broke out within days.
A significant increase
in the total average number
of acne lesions
within 4 days.
And, same thing
with more chronic
dark chocolate consumption:
a half a small chocolate
bar a day for a month,
and increased acne severity
was reported within 2 weeks,
with before-and-after
pictures looking like this.
OK, but what was lacking
in these two studies?
Give people chocolate every day
and their acne gets worse,
or one big load of chocolate
and their acne gets worse.
What didn’t these
studies include?
Long-time NutritionFacts followers
should know this by now.
Right, they’re missing
a control group.
If you look at surveys,
most people believe
chocolate causes acne;
so, if you give people a
big load of chocolate,
maybe just the stress
and expectation
that they’re going
to have an outbreak
contributes to the
actual outbreak.
To really get to
the bottom of this,
you’d have to
design a study
where you give people
disguised chocolate.
You expose people to chocolate
without them knowing it
and see if they
still break out.
Like you could
put cocoa powder
into opaque capsules,
so they don’t know
if they’re getting
cocoa or placebo,
and that would have
the additional benefit
of eliminating the cocoa
butter fat factor.
No milk, no sugar, no fat,
just pure cocoa powder in
capsules versus placebo,
but there's never been
such a study until...
Now.
A double-blind, placebo-controlled
study assessing the effects of
chocolate consumption,
actually cocoa powder consumption,
in subjects with
a history of acne –
assigned to swallow capsules
filled with either
unsweetened 100% cocoa,
or a placebo of like an unflavored,
unsweetened jello powder.
Just a one-time binge
requiring the swallowing
of up to 240 capsules to try to
secretly expose people
to a few ounces
of cocoa powder and…
the same significant increase,
the same doubling
of acne lesions
within 4 days,
like in the Ghirardelli study.
So, sadly, it
really does appear
that in acne-prone individuals,
the consumption of cocoa
may cause an increase in acne.
Now, the study did
just include men;
so, they didn’t have to deal
with cyclical
hormonal changes,
and it’s hard to imagine
that the real cocoa group,
after swallowing
hundreds of capsules,
didn’t burp up some cocoa taste
and know they were not
just in the placebo group.
But, the best available
balance of evidence
does suggest that if
you’re bothered by acne,
you may want to try backing off
on chocolate to see
if your symptoms improve.